<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: howto | Random Software Inklings]]></title>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/categories/howto/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-28T22:27:55-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John T. Kamenik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crafty Timer]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/02/24/crafty-timer/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-24T13:28:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/02/24/crafty-timer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Crafty JS is a game engine written in Javascript.  Like many game engines there is a main event loop that drives everything.  This is actually a great thing, unless you are trying to use timers.</p>

<p>Javascript is single threaded but asynchronous.  This means there is no way to "sleep" the main loop.  Instead there is a <code>setTimeout</code> function which takes a callback that is called after the timer has expired.  In most JS programs having one or more timers setup via <code>setTimeout</code> isn't much of an issue.</p>

<p>In Crafty there is already a main event loop that actually performs the same function and it better fits the separation of background and rendering responsibilities.  Remember that in a game you will have hundreds or thousands of background calculation per second but only 40 to 60 rendering calculations.</p>

<p>With that in mind I created two components: a Timer which does everything in the background, and TimePrinter which is a timer and rerenders the current seconds until the timer expires.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Timer</h2>

<p>```coffeescript timer.coffee
Crafty.c('Timer',{
  <em>stopFunc:    null,
  </em>expireTime:  null,
  _secondsLeft: null,</p>

<p>  start: -></p>

<pre><code>return if this._stopFunc
return if this._calculateTime &lt;= 0

self = this
this._stopFunc = Crafty.bind('EnterFrame', -&gt;
  # a proxy callback which sets the "this"
  self._calculateTime()
)
this
</code></pre>

<p>  stop: -></p>

<pre><code>return unless this._stopFunc
Crafty.unbind('EnterFrame', this._stopFunc)
this._stopFunc = null
this
</code></pre>

<p>  expiresIn: (seconds, autoStart = false)-></p>

<pre><code>this._expireTime = Date.now() + (seconds * 1000)
this.start() if autoStart
this
</code></pre>

<p>  addSeconds: (seconds, autoStart = false)-></p>

<pre><code>this._expireTime = Date.now() if this._secondsLeft &lt;= 0
this._expireTime += (seconds * 1000)
this.start() if autoStart
this
</code></pre>

<p>  _calculateTime: (event)-></p>

<pre><code>now  = Date.now()
left = this._expireTime - now
this._secondsLeft = Math.floor(left / 1000)

this.stop() if this._secondsLeft &lt;= 0
this._secondsLeft
</code></pre>

<p>})
```</p>

<p><code>start</code> starts the timer.  It binds to the "EnterFrame" event and sets up a proxy callback to ensure the "this" variable is maintained during the callback.</p>

<p><code>stop</code> remotes the "EnterFrame" callback thereby detacting it from the timer loop.</p>

<p><code>expiresIn</code> sets up a number of seconds to expire the timer in.  There is an optional second paramter to start the timer loop.</p>

<p><code>addSeconds</code> adds seconds to the existing timer, making it take longer to expire.  If the timer has expired then it behaves like <code>expiresIn</code></p>

<p><code>_calculateTime</code> is the work horse.  It calculates the real time and compares it to the expire time and returns the number of seconds until it expires.  If the current time is greater or equal to the expire time then the timer is considered expired and is stopped.  Stopping the timer removes any useless calculations, speeding up the overall game.</p>

<h2>Time Printer</h2>

<p>In order to separate concerns I created a separate component to print the number of seconds until the timer expires.  By separating things out I can have a general purpose timer which is displayed many different ways.</p>

<p>This class simply shows the number of seconds left as a string.</p>

<p>```coffeescript time_printer.js
Crafty.c('TimePrinter',{
  init: -></p>

<pre><code>this.requires '2D, DOM, Text, Timer'
this.attr({
  x: 100,
  y: 100,
  w: 200
})
self = this
this.bind('RenderScene',-&gt;
  self.render()
)
</code></pre>

<p>  render: -></p>

<pre><code>this.text ''+this._secondsLeft+' seconds'
</code></pre>

<p>})
```</p>

<p><code>init</code> requires the DOM, 2D, and Text components so that I can render text.  It also requires Timer so that it behaves like a Timer.  It also binds to the "RenderScene" event, which just rendering thread.</p>

<p><code>render</code> is the call back called when it is time to render the entity.</p>

<h2>Usage</h2>

<p>A simple usage might look something like this:</p>

<p><code>coffeescript scene/loading.coffee
Crafty.scene('Loading',-&gt;
  printer = Crafty.e("TimePrinter")
  printer.expiresIn 10, true
)
</code></p>

<p>```html timer.html
<html>
<head></p>

<pre><code>&lt;script src="lib/crafty.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src="src/components/timer.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src="src/components/time_printer.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src="src/scenes/loading.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
  window.addEventListener('load',-&gt;
    Crafty.init()

    Crafty.scene('Loading')
  )
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    body { 
        padding: 0;
        margin:  0;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></head>
<body></body>
</html>
```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Drafts]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/01/21/drafts/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-21T11:38:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/01/21/drafts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Jekyll supports unpublished posts, but Octopress does not make it clear.  This is how I fixed that for my own blog.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Octopress actually does support "published: false" in the front matter.  And because it based on Jekyll it means that those posts will be available in "preview" but will be ignored when the site is generated/published.</p>

<p>My main care is that I know what I can do with a post in 3 to 4 months.  So I added the the published flag to the generated frontmatter of every new post.</p>

<p>```ruby Rakefile</p>

<h1>around line 93, for me</h1>

<p>task :new_post, :title do |t, args|
  # code omitted
  open(filename, 'w') do |post|</p>

<pre><code>post.puts "---"
post.puts "layout: post"
post.puts "title: \"#{title.gsub(/&amp;/,'&amp;amp;')}\""
post.puts "date: #{Time.now.strftime('%Y-%m-%d %H:%M')}"
post.puts "comments: true"
post.puts "toc: false"
# add published flag to the template
post.puts "published: false"
post.puts "categories: "
post.puts "  - cat1"
post.puts "---"
post.puts
post.puts "Summary"
post.puts
post.puts "&lt;!-- more --&gt;"
post.puts
post.puts "Post text"
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>I also had to update <code>rake push</code> to regenerate the full site before deployment.  This is because preview works on the same directly that is copied to production.  And since you can preview unpublished posts they will be visible in production, unless you run <code>rake generate</code> first.</p>

<p>```ruby Rakefile</p>

<h1>around line 254</h1>

<p>multitask :push do
  # add the generate rake task first
  Rake::Task[:generate].invoke
  # code omitted
end
```</p>

<p>Additionally I want to know visually when a page is a draft.  For that I add "Draft: " to the title.</p>

<p>```html _includes/article.html
</p>

<h1>in the <header> tag</h1>

<p>{% if index %}
  # add {% if post.published == false %}Draft: {% endif %}
  <h1 class="entry-title"><a href="{{ root_url }}{{ post.url }}">{% if post.published == false %}Draft: {% endif %}{% if site.titlecase %}{{ post.title | titlecase }}{% else %}{{ post.title }}{% endif %}</a></h1>
{% else %}
  # add {% if page.published == false %}Draft: {% endif %}
  <h1 class="entry-title">{% if page.published == false %}Draft: {% endif %}{% if site.titlecase %}{{ page.title | titlecase }}{% else %}{{ page.title }}{% endif %}</h1>
{% endif %}

```</p>

<p>Now you will see "Draft: " in front of any unpublished posts.</p>

<h2>Manual management</h2>

<p>A few additional things I like to do, but I haven't automated yet are:</p>

<ol>
<li>Add "-draft" to the file name.</li>
<li>Change the publish date to the day I publish the article

<ol>
<li>This involves changing the file name as well as the front matter</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RBAC in Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/01/10/rbac-in-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-10T15:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/01/10/rbac-in-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>RBAC stands for <em>Role Based Access Control</em>.  It is basically a means to programmitically configure access rights without hardcoding.</p>

<p>The full details are <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Role-based_access_control">here</a>, but to be honest I don't fully understand it as writen.  What I understand of it is from trial and error.</p>

<p>This entry is an attempt to codify that understanding and apply it using the ruby language.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Basics</h2>

<p>The inputs to the policy are:</p>

<ol>
<li>User or Actor</li>
<li>Action being performed</li>
<li>Resource being acted on</li>
</ol>


<pre>
    +-------------------------------------------------------+
    | +-------+                                +----------+ |
    | |       |            +------+            |          | |
    | |  User |+---------->|Action|+---------->| Resource | |
    | |       |            +------+            |          | |
    | +-------+                                +----------+ |
    +-------------------------------------------------------+
                               +
                               |
                               v
                            +------+
                            |Policy|
                            +------+
                               +
                               |
                               v
                          +---------+
                          |Yes or No|
                          +---------+
</pre>


<h2>Policy</h2>

<p>The policy is where the business logic goes.  It can be as simple as a set of Ruby classes that simply return values, or it can be as complicated as ActiveDirectory.</p>

<p>The players are:</p>

<ol>
<li>Role - collection of permissions bound to a user</li>
<li>Permission - an answer which is limited to a resource and action</li>
</ol>


<p>Here is the basic flow of a permission:</p>

<pre>
    +------+            +------+             +------------+
    | User |+---------->| Role |+----------->| Permission |
    +------+            +------+             |------------|
              Has many            Has many   | Resource   |
                                             | Action     |
                                             | Allowed?   |
                                             +------------+
</pre>


<p>A user can have 1 or more roles.  Each role can have 1 or more permissions.  Each permission associates an action on a resource with an answer.  Either the user is explicitly allowed or explicitly not allowed to access the Resource.</p>

<p><em>Note:</em> I have purposely kept the data model simple.  In more complicated setups there can be several levels of permissions, permissions can have filters, and/or permissions can be directly bound to a user (instead of being bound to a role).  These complications are often introduced to deal with edge cases which are outside the scope of this article.</p>

<h3>Policy logic sample code</h3>

<p>Once the actors are known the logic is easy.  Simply filter in only the permission on a user for the resource and action in question then "and" all permissions together.</p>

<p>```ruby
class Policy</p>

<pre><code># returns true if the user *can* perform action on resource, false otherwise
def allowed?(user,action,resource)
    reduce_permissions list_permissions(user,action,resource)
end
</code></pre>

<p>private</p>

<pre><code># returns an array of filtered permissions
def list_permissions(user,action,resource)
    perm = user.roles.inject([]) do |array,role|
        array.concat role.permissions.for(resource).with(action).compact
    end
end

def reduce_permissions(perm_array)
    return implicit_allow if perm_array.empty?

    perm_array.reduce(true,:&amp;&amp;)
end

# "and", for "or" use ":||"
def reduce_function
    :&amp;&amp;
end

# default behavior is NOT to give access
def implicit_allow
    false
end
</code></pre>

<p>end
```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Automator - Start work - workflow]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2013/09/10/automator-workflow/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T09:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2013/09/10/automator-workflow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't like to repeat myself, and I use a Mac, so I have a great little tool called "Automator".  Every morning when I am about to start work I open Spotlight (<code>cmd + space</code> for me) and type "startwork".  The first app that shows up is my Automator workflow for opening all the programs that I need to work.</p>

<p>Here is my Automator workflow:</p>

<p><img src="/images/start-work.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The apple script (The first action)</h2>

<p>This is a template apple script that just launches all my applications.</p>

<ol>
<li>Adium - An OS X chat client that can almost all IM protocols.</li>
<li>Waterfall Campfire - My company's campfire chatroom isolated inside a Fluid app.</li>
<li>iTerm - My terminal of choice.</li>
<li>Tower - My git client of choice.</li>
<li>RubyMine - My IDE of choice.</li>
</ol>


<p><em>Note: I use "activate" with iTerm, because "launch" throws an error</em></p>

<h3>Assigning apps to desktops</h3>

<p>Automator cannot do this for you (at least not yet).  But I am very particular about where and how I like my windows setup.  Luckily the Mac remembers the last window settings on exit, so moving things around, resizing windows, and quitting does the trick.  However, it does <strong>not</strong> remember which screen an app is on.</p>

<p>To assign an app to open on a specific screen follow these steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Open the app</li>
<li>Move the app to the screen you want (using mission control)</li>
<li>Switch to that screen</li>
<li>In the dock

<ol>
<li>Right click the application icon</li>
<li>Click Options -> Assign To -> This desktop</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>


<p><em>Note: this only effects where the app opens, you can move windows to other screens anytime you want</em></p>

<h2>Opening URLs (Last 3 actions)</h2>

<p>The last three actions are the easiest way I can find to open multiple URLs in the same browser at once.  The automator task uses the system's default browser which for me is Chrome.</p>

<p><em>Note: the URLs are opened in a semi-random order.  I don't know how to fix that.</em></p>

<p>I like to open URLs as close to where I actually do my work as possible.  The trick is hacking the URLs.  These are the URLs that I use most.  Other URLs come and go - like right now where I open github.</p>

<ol>
<li>Pivotal Tracker - https://www.pivotaltracker.com/s/projects/<code>project id</code>

<ol>
<li>I tend to work on a single project for long periods of time so I just open that project every time.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Google Mail - https://mail.google.com/mail/u/<code>multi-login index</code>

<ol>
<li>The <code>/u/...</code> tells google to open a different logged in account.  I <em>always</em> log into my personal gmail account first (index 0) and my work account second.  So <code>/u/1</code> is my work email.</li>
<li>If you add <code>/u/...</code> but aren't logged into google multiple times it will ask you to login again.  This can be jarring if you are not expecting it.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Basecamp - https://basecamp.com/<code>account-id</code></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Keynote for Mockups]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2013/08/29/using-keynote-for-mockups/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-29T08:47:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2013/08/29/using-keynote-for-mockups</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are a lot of UI mockup software out there.  I am sure they are good, but chances are that you already have exactly what you need.  I used to ominigraffle, which was fine.  And I know people that use Visio.  And there are a ton of UI Mocking software out there that costs a ton.</p>

<p>However, I have found presentation software (specifically Keynote) already has all the features you need for a good UI mockup.</p>

<p>Features of Keynote:</p>

<ol>
<li>Almost everyone knows how to create a presentation</li>
<li>$20 on the app store (that is not a sales price)</li>
<li>Presentation ready</li>
<li>Master slides, which allows

<ol>
<li>Crafting static backgrounds</li>
<li>Text placeholders</li>
<li>Custom guidelines</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Hidden slides

<ol>
<li>Allows for templating common items, but not showing them in the presentation</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Clickable elements

<ol>
<li>Allows simulating of a working UI.</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>


<!-- more -->


<p>Here is my step by step for creating UI mockups.</p>

<h2>1. Use pen and paper</h2>

<p>Paper and Pen are the fastest way to get your ideas out of your head.  The other good thing about pen and paper is that you are not nessissarly constrained by UI medaphores built into a computer.  If you are trying to think of a better way to do something using a computer that is subtly forcing your into common UI patterns then that is the direction you will head.  You will not end up with anything better then before and you will likely have wasted a lot of time doing it.</p>

<p>Paper is supposed to be fast, not perfect.  So only use standard printer paper and a black pen.  Nothing more.</p>

<h3>1.1 Paper layout</h3>

<p>Fold the paper like <a href="/images/paper_in_8s.jpg">this</a>.</p>

<p>This gives you 16 slides to play with (8 on each side).  Also, it roughly simulates landscape and portrait layout of a screen.  I recommend sacrificing one slide with a orientation arrow (point to the top of the sheet) and short title.  Definitely not a requirement, but it helps when you come back to these slides after a week.</p>

<h3>1.2. The shotgun</h3>

<p>Take part of the UI metaphor and shotgun different ideas on all 16 slides (15 if you want to keep a title).  Spend no more then 10minutes on it, or about 35s / slide.  All you are trying to do is come up with ideas on what might work.</p>

<p>After that spend some time on each slide deciding what does and does not work.  Cross out the complete failures.  Circle things you like.</p>

<p>Repeat this as much as you need to.</p>

<h3>1.3 Story-board</h3>

<p>If you are creating a multipart UI then take everything that worked and story-board out the progression.  Use only the elements that worked.  You might find that when story-boarded things, that you thought would work, don't work.  There is not harm shotgunning some new ideas.</p>

<p>Each state of the UI is a single slide.  For example, if I am looking to demo a warning message when a user checks a checkbox then I would draw one frame with the button unchecked and no warning, and another with the button checked and a warning.  You can fill in the rest of the slides with other states or you can leave them blank.</p>

<h3>1.4 The reveal</h3>

<p>Don't give a formal presentation.  Just show your slides and explain what you are trying to do.  Ideas will fly, so take notes.</p>

<p>One of two things will happen during the reveal: 1) the ideas are fine, but need a little work.  Or 2) everything about the idea is wrong.  If there are only minor tweaks then I recommend <strong>not</strong> redoing anything paper and instead moving on to more formal design.</p>

<p>If everything is wrong then stop now.  No harm, no foul.  You either didn't have enough to go on, or your ideas weren't clean.  Either way you only spent 10 to 20 minutes on something that was likely to fail anyway.  It probably best if the project is scrapped or rethought.</p>

<h3>How do I share paper with remote workers?</h3>

<p>Good question!  That is why white paper without lines, and a blank pen are so important.</p>

<p>You share the document by scanning it with a scanner (if you work in an office) or you take a picture of it with your smart phone!</p>

<h2>2. Setup a master document</h2>

<p>Keynote isn't really meant for everyone to edit at the same time.  But you can create a master document which you share with the team so that everyone is on the same page.</p>

<ol>
<li>Start by creating a new document with the "White".</li>
<li>Open the "Master Slides" menu: View -> Show Master Slides</li>
<li>Delete all the master slides except "Title &amp; subtitle" and "Blank"</li>
<li>Fill out the title slide</li>
</ol>


<h2>3. Template common elements</h2>

<p>At this point you should have a rough set of slides or a story-board and the basic master document.  You may have 10s or 100s of slides that need to be converted to digital, but before any of that create common UI elements.</p>

<p><a href="http://keynotopia.com/">http://keynotopia.com/</a> and things like it can be purchased to augment your UI collection.  Copy over or create the UI elements that are present in your story board.</p>

<p>Once you have a good set of common UI elements in one or two slides mark them skipped slide: Slide -> Skip slide.  This will let you later copy and paste elements but skip the slide during presentations.</p>

<h2>4. Create common backgrounds (using master slides)</h2>

<p>Just like creating common UI element, creating master slides lets you quickly throw together backgrounds.  More importantly editing the master slides causes every slide to update.</p>

<p>A master slide is just like a normal slide except that it can be used as the base for other sides.  For that reason anything that you put in a master side is not editable in a normal slide.  The exception is text which can be marked as a placeholder and changed in the slide.</p>

<p>I recommend building master slides in the following manner.</p>

<h3>4.1 Background object</h3>

<p>As a standard slide you can put any objects including shapes, and text.  The rule of thumb is to start with a recognizable background.  For websites that means creating something that looks like a web browser.  For a iPhone app create the outline of an iPhone.  For a computer program create common window.</p>

<p>Since these objects aren't editable in slides you may find that you create quite a few master slides with different aspects of the project.  That is a good thing.  You master slides will ballon as your design balloons, which is another form of feedback.</p>

<p><strong>Tip</strong>: You may also want to create a slide that simulates scrolling to the middle or bottom of the page.  Just add a right scroll bar to the right at different positions: top, middle, bottom.</p>

<h3>4.2 Guides</h3>

<p>Once you have the master slide objects in place you will notice that the center of the usable area will not be centered the center of the slide.  This makes it difficult to position things on slides in a consistent way.  To make it easy again add guides.</p>

<p>Show the rulers: View -> Show Rulers.  Then grabbing the top ruler and dragging down will add a horizontal guide.  Grabbing the left ruler and dragging right will add a vertical guide.</p>

<p><strong>Tip:</strong> I add guides on the edges (like the sides of the iPhone screen).  Then I add guides in the middle.  Sometimes I will also add guides at the golden mean, or thirds, but never both at the same time.</p>

<h3>4.3 Placeholders</h3>

<p>Any text box can be a placeholder which means that the text can be modified on the slide.  When doing a website I make the browser title and URL bar a placeholder.</p>

<p>To create a placeholder first add a "Text box", place it where you want, and give it a good default value.  With the item selected open the <strong>Inspector</strong> and go to the <em>Master Slide</em> tab.  Check "Define as Text Placeholder" and give it a unique name.</p>

<p>A slide can modify a placeholder in any way it needs to.  This includes changing size, position, or even deleting the item entirely.  But it is a really good way to add quickly configurable defaults.</p>

<h2>5. Create UI (using slides)</h2>

<p>With the master slides and templates in place it is a simple matter to create slides.  A slide should contain no more then would fit on a single screen; remember presentation slides don't scroll.  If you need a multipage slide split it over 2 or 3 slides.</p>

<p>Do not try to make the screen interactive.  That is not the purpose of a presentation.  Stick with duplicating the paper slides.</p>

<h2>6. Create interaction (using clickable items)</h2>

<p>You could stop at step 5 and give a pretty great presentation, but sometimes you really want to take things over the top.  Keynote allows you to make objects hyperlinks, which can link to another slide, a webpage, or another presentation.</p>

<p>In the design view there is a visual clue that the item is clickable, but not during the presentation.  And since hyperlinks can jump forward or backwards in the presentation this feature can get you into a lot of trouble.  It is very important that the entire presentation be closed to finished before adding hyperlinks.</p>

<p><strong>Tip:</strong> To help you stay out of trouble, duplicate a slide and only change one item.  Then link from the first slide to the second in a way that makes sense, and be sure to link from the second back to the first.  Resist the urge to have the second slide link anywhere but to the first slide.</p>

<h2>7. Don't Add details</h2>

<p>You can spend hours adding details which will either need to be completely removed and redone or will be ignored.  The goal is to provide enough fidelity to be useful but not enough detail to reach the "uncanny valley" of sorts.  If the fidelity of the design is too high then people start picking apart the details, and stop thinking about the presentation.</p>

<h3>Uncanny Valley</h3>

<p>This is a term borrowed from the field of human aesthetics that states "[it] is the region of negative emotional response towards robots that seem 'almost human'".  See the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncanny_valley">wikipedia article</a> for details.</p>

<p>The issue doesn't stop with humans judging humans, it takes place anytime a human judges something that seems familiar.  Especially computer programs.  Basically, as we add detail there is a point right before "perfect" which is so bad that it is worse then if stopped at the hand drawings.</p>

<ol>
<li>Nothing -> neutral</li>
<li>Drawings -> good</li>
<li>Keynote -> better</li>
<li>Keynote with details -> <strong>HORRIBLE!!!!</strong></li>
<li>Actual implementation -> best</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
