<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ronin | Random Software Inklings]]></title>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/categories/ronin/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-15T21:56:47-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John T. Kamenik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ronin Avery Kamenik]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/02/28/ronin-avery-kamenik/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-28T14:29:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/02/28/ronin-avery-kamenik</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Born February 21st, 2014 at 7:04am.  8lbs 11oz, 21 3/4 inches.</p>

<p><img src="/images/ronin/IMG_0454.jpeg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Timeline</h2>

<p><strong>Wednesday 2/19</strong> Mel starts having labor.  The contractors were about 10 minutes apart and between 30s and 1m.  They slow and stop by noon.</p>

<p><strong>Thursday 12am</strong> Contractions start again and are fairly regular.  Just need to wait until they are 5 minutes apart before we start calling people.</p>

<p><strong>1am</strong> Contractions are 5 minutes apart so we call Mel's family to come down and pick up Frankie, call my family to come and pick up the dogs, and call the Doula.</p>

<p><strong>2:15am</strong> Doula arrived.  And after a bit we decide to call the Midwife.  The midwife tells us to wait another hour</p>

<p><strong>3am</strong> Mel's parents arrive.</p>

<p><strong>3:45am</strong> We leave for the Hospital.</p>

<p><strong>5am</strong> We are in triage.  And they are running tests.</p>

<p><strong>5:40am</strong> We are discharged, because we are only 2cm dilated.  You have to be 4 to 5 cm to be admitted.</p>

<p><strong>6:30am</strong> We are home again, and try to relax.</p>

<p><strong>11am</strong> Midwife appointment.  We are 5cm dilated.  They tell us to go walk around for 2 hours and report to the hospital again.  We head to the near by Annapolis mall to eat lunch, and walk around.  I am massaging Mel’s back as she has contractions while we walk.  People stare but we don’t care.</p>

<p><strong>1:30pm</strong> Go back to the hospital, are admitted and settle into our room.</p>

<p><strong>7pm</strong> Not making much progress so they give us some options: go home, stay have the water broken and risk the C-Section.  We counter with stay but walk.  They allow us to unhook from the monitors and walk the halls.  So we walk constantly for 2+ hours.</p>

<p><strong>11pm</strong> Re-checked and she had progressed to 8 cm dilated.  Walking really did the trick.</p>

<p><strong>Friday 12am</strong> Water spontaneously broke while laying in bed.  I was holding her hand through the contractions, in socks.  You can imagine what happened to the those socks :)</p>

<p>Now we are on the clock.  Mel is still at 8cm, and Ronin is at -2 station.  There are still many hours of labor left.</p>

<p>About 10 minutes after the water broke the first dry contraction starts.  It many many many times more powerful and painful then the back labor she has been dealing with so far.  Mel (against her birth plan) wants an epidural.  The doula, nurse, and I are getting Mel through the contractions one at a time, by being positive and telling her she can do it.</p>

<p>The hardest part is getting Mel relaxed after the contractions, but they are coming every few seconds.  After many contractions we relent and agree on the epidural if she promises to take a nap so that when it is time to push she is ready.</p>

<p>(As an aside, she probably could have gone a lot further without the meds, but with so little sleep we were risking another C-Section if she was too tired to push)</p>

<p><strong>12:30am</strong> The epidural is put in, which is difficult because you have to remain still and relaxed.  Pretty much impossible when you are contracting, so the Dr has to work between contractions.</p>

<p>After the epidural is in we settle down for our first sleep since Tuesday.  Its not going to be great sleep, but we all know that the hardest part is yet to come.</p>

<p><strong>6am</strong> Mel feels an almost uncontrollable urge to poop, which is a sign that she needs to start pushing.  This is hardest part.</p>

<p>We have to wait until we are seen by the Midwife.  After we are checked we get the news that Mel is 9+ cm dilated but Ronin is still at -1 / -2 station.  This means that he has not yet engaged.  He should be at 0 or 1 by this point.</p>

<p>The Midwife suggests that Mel perform some practice pushing just to get Ronin engaged.  Then we can take another nap and start again.</p>

<p>The next time Mel feels the urge she pushes, while the Doula and I hold her legs.  She pushed him to engagement, so the Midwife starts massaging the cervix to get it around his head.  A few pushes later Ronin is descending.  The Midwife is very happy with the quality, strength, and duration of Mel's pushes.</p>

<p><strong>6:45am</strong> The Midwife points out the very top of Ronin's head, which is just visible, and doesn't retract between pushes.  This means that Mel's "practice" pushing will actually birth Ronin.</p>

<p>About 3 pushes later and he is fully crowning.  The Midwife holds her hand on Ronin's head to prevent him from ejecting and calls for a gown.  The room is teaming with Doctors and nurses now, and she is given freedom to push.</p>

<p>1 push and the head is out.  Couple pushes later his shoulders.</p>

<p><strong>7:04am</strong> Ronin is born and laying on Mel's chest.  They give her a few moments before taking him for clean up and scoring.</p>

<p><strong>8am</strong> Everything went well.  Ronin has a 1 minute Apgar score of 8 and 5 minute score of 9.  He is looking great and we are left alone for several hours to enjoy our new baby.</p>

<p><strong>10am</strong> The nurse comes back in to give Ronin his first bath, and check him over again.  They are still waiting for a recovery room to become free so we remain in the delivery room.</p>

<p><strong>3pm</strong> They have a recovery room for us. So we move.  Ronin was a no risk delivery, so they only need to observe him for 24 hours from the first feeding, which was about 7:30.  We elect to leave as soon as possible.</p>

<p><strong>Saturday 2pm</strong> Ronin has had all the tests done, and the lactation consult has been in to help Mel with breast feeding, and we are free to leave.  Breast feeding is going much easier with Ronin; 90% of it is that Mel is more relaxed.</p>

<p>With our first, leaving the hospital was a nerveracking time, but with our second we already know what we are doing, and we already have all the stuff.  We are ready to go.  I can't wait to sleep in my own bed, next to my wife.</p>

<h2>What I have learned (this time)</h2>

<p>Each baby is different, and I am not a medical professional.  Everything I listed here is true for my baby only.</p>

<ol>
<li>Each baby is different.  For example:

<ol>
<li>Frankie slept for the first week, even sleeping through feedings.  Ronin was awake for several hours after birth, and spends several hours a day awake.</li>
<li>Frankie could lift his head after 1 week.  Ronin was born with the ability to lift his head.</li>
<li>Frankie was easier to carry because he was a lump.  Ronin moves a lot and throws his head around and is much harder to carry when he is awake.</li>
<li>Frankie didn’t care to be held.  Ronin prefers to be held.</li>
<li>Frankie prefers to sit in his own filth rather than being changed.  Ronin hates to be dirty and prefers to be changed.</li>
<li>Frankie fit well into a size bigger (3 month clothes when he was born).  Ronin is slightly longer than Frankie, but lighter so nothing fits him correctly.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Each pregnancy is different

<ol>
<li>Each pregnancy gets harder.  The pains hurt worse during pregnancy and the after pains are wrose as well.</li>
<li>Each pregnancy gets easier.  Even though everything hurts more you are expecting it, and can better deal with it.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Life is hardest after the first one.  It is hard to go from “without kids” to “with kids”.  But once you are “with kids” two kids is not that much harder than one.  You have already baby proofed the house, and changed your life around.</li>
<li>Allowing comments on your baby’s birth story is stupid.  I learned that after the first one.  Therefore I have disabled them on this one.  Sorry for anyone that wants to wish us well, but one can ruin it for everyone.</li>
<li>Sleep is less of an issue with the 2nd.  To be honest we get a lot less sleep this time around.  The difference is that we know we are going to get sleep 30 minutes at a time.  And we love it when he gives us more.  With Frankie we were scared to sleep because we should only get 1 hour or so.</li>
<li>A vaginal birth is front loaded, while a C-Section is back loaded.  I am not a proponent for one vs the other, but in our case the C-Section was over and done with in a matter of minutes.  The vaginal birth took hours (31 to be exact).  In the C-Section case, all of the recovery started after the birth with 3 days in the hospital.  With the VBAC once the delivery was over we were free to go.  So with Vaginal birth (assuming there are no complications) everything happens leading up to the birth, with a C-Section everything happens after the birth.</li>
<li>Writing a birth plan, having a Doula, and using Midwifes was ideal for us.  Everyone was really supportive, and the Doula stayed with us the entire time.  The midwives and nurses reviewed the birth plan and where very engaged with us if there were reasons we had to go off plan.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
