<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: fatherhood | Random Software Inklings]]></title>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/categories/fatherhood/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-23T16:54:03-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John T. Kamenik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ronin Avery Kamenik]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/02/28/ronin-avery-kamenik/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-28T14:29:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/02/28/ronin-avery-kamenik</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Born February 21st, 2014 at 7:04am.  8lbs 11oz, 21 3/4 inches.</p>

<p><img src="/images/ronin/IMG_0454.jpeg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Timeline</h2>

<p><strong>Wednesday 2/19</strong> Mel starts having labor.  The contractors were about 10 minutes apart and between 30s and 1m.  They slow and stop by noon.</p>

<p><strong>Thursday 12am</strong> Contractions start again and are fairly regular.  Just need to wait until they are 5 minutes apart before we start calling people.</p>

<p><strong>1am</strong> Contractions are 5 minutes apart so we call Mel's family to come down and pick up Frankie, call my family to come and pick up the dogs, and call the Doula.</p>

<p><strong>2:15am</strong> Doula arrived.  And after a bit we decide to call the Midwife.  The midwife tells us to wait another hour</p>

<p><strong>3am</strong> Mel's parents arrive.</p>

<p><strong>3:45am</strong> We leave for the Hospital.</p>

<p><strong>5am</strong> We are in triage.  And they are running tests.</p>

<p><strong>5:40am</strong> We are discharged, because we are only 2cm dilated.  You have to be 4 to 5 cm to be admitted.</p>

<p><strong>6:30am</strong> We are home again, and try to relax.</p>

<p><strong>11am</strong> Midwife appointment.  We are 5cm dilated.  They tell us to go walk around for 2 hours and report to the hospital again.  We head to the near by Annapolis mall to eat lunch, and walk around.  I am massaging Mel’s back as she has contractions while we walk.  People stare but we don’t care.</p>

<p><strong>1:30pm</strong> Go back to the hospital, are admitted and settle into our room.</p>

<p><strong>7pm</strong> Not making much progress so they give us some options: go home, stay have the water broken and risk the C-Section.  We counter with stay but walk.  They allow us to unhook from the monitors and walk the halls.  So we walk constantly for 2+ hours.</p>

<p><strong>11pm</strong> Re-checked and she had progressed to 8 cm dilated.  Walking really did the trick.</p>

<p><strong>Friday 12am</strong> Water spontaneously broke while laying in bed.  I was holding her hand through the contractions, in socks.  You can imagine what happened to the those socks :)</p>

<p>Now we are on the clock.  Mel is still at 8cm, and Ronin is at -2 station.  There are still many hours of labor left.</p>

<p>About 10 minutes after the water broke the first dry contraction starts.  It many many many times more powerful and painful then the back labor she has been dealing with so far.  Mel (against her birth plan) wants an epidural.  The doula, nurse, and I are getting Mel through the contractions one at a time, by being positive and telling her she can do it.</p>

<p>The hardest part is getting Mel relaxed after the contractions, but they are coming every few seconds.  After many contractions we relent and agree on the epidural if she promises to take a nap so that when it is time to push she is ready.</p>

<p>(As an aside, she probably could have gone a lot further without the meds, but with so little sleep we were risking another C-Section if she was too tired to push)</p>

<p><strong>12:30am</strong> The epidural is put in, which is difficult because you have to remain still and relaxed.  Pretty much impossible when you are contracting, so the Dr has to work between contractions.</p>

<p>After the epidural is in we settle down for our first sleep since Tuesday.  Its not going to be great sleep, but we all know that the hardest part is yet to come.</p>

<p><strong>6am</strong> Mel feels an almost uncontrollable urge to poop, which is a sign that she needs to start pushing.  This is hardest part.</p>

<p>We have to wait until we are seen by the Midwife.  After we are checked we get the news that Mel is 9+ cm dilated but Ronin is still at -1 / -2 station.  This means that he has not yet engaged.  He should be at 0 or 1 by this point.</p>

<p>The Midwife suggests that Mel perform some practice pushing just to get Ronin engaged.  Then we can take another nap and start again.</p>

<p>The next time Mel feels the urge she pushes, while the Doula and I hold her legs.  She pushed him to engagement, so the Midwife starts massaging the cervix to get it around his head.  A few pushes later Ronin is descending.  The Midwife is very happy with the quality, strength, and duration of Mel's pushes.</p>

<p><strong>6:45am</strong> The Midwife points out the very top of Ronin's head, which is just visible, and doesn't retract between pushes.  This means that Mel's "practice" pushing will actually birth Ronin.</p>

<p>About 3 pushes later and he is fully crowning.  The Midwife holds her hand on Ronin's head to prevent him from ejecting and calls for a gown.  The room is teaming with Doctors and nurses now, and she is given freedom to push.</p>

<p>1 push and the head is out.  Couple pushes later his shoulders.</p>

<p><strong>7:04am</strong> Ronin is born and laying on Mel's chest.  They give her a few moments before taking him for clean up and scoring.</p>

<p><strong>8am</strong> Everything went well.  Ronin has a 1 minute Apgar score of 8 and 5 minute score of 9.  He is looking great and we are left alone for several hours to enjoy our new baby.</p>

<p><strong>10am</strong> The nurse comes back in to give Ronin his first bath, and check him over again.  They are still waiting for a recovery room to become free so we remain in the delivery room.</p>

<p><strong>3pm</strong> They have a recovery room for us. So we move.  Ronin was a no risk delivery, so they only need to observe him for 24 hours from the first feeding, which was about 7:30.  We elect to leave as soon as possible.</p>

<p><strong>Saturday 2pm</strong> Ronin has had all the tests done, and the lactation consult has been in to help Mel with breast feeding, and we are free to leave.  Breast feeding is going much easier with Ronin; 90% of it is that Mel is more relaxed.</p>

<p>With our first, leaving the hospital was a nerveracking time, but with our second we already know what we are doing, and we already have all the stuff.  We are ready to go.  I can't wait to sleep in my own bed, next to my wife.</p>

<h2>What I have learned (this time)</h2>

<p>Each baby is different, and I am not a medical professional.  Everything I listed here is true for my baby only.</p>

<ol>
<li>Each baby is different.  For example:

<ol>
<li>Frankie slept for the first week, even sleeping through feedings.  Ronin was awake for several hours after birth, and spends several hours a day awake.</li>
<li>Frankie could lift his head after 1 week.  Ronin was born with the ability to lift his head.</li>
<li>Frankie was easier to carry because he was a lump.  Ronin moves a lot and throws his head around and is much harder to carry when he is awake.</li>
<li>Frankie didn’t care to be held.  Ronin prefers to be held.</li>
<li>Frankie prefers to sit in his own filth rather than being changed.  Ronin hates to be dirty and prefers to be changed.</li>
<li>Frankie fit well into a size bigger (3 month clothes when he was born).  Ronin is slightly longer than Frankie, but lighter so nothing fits him correctly.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Each pregnancy is different

<ol>
<li>Each pregnancy gets harder.  The pains hurt worse during pregnancy and the after pains are wrose as well.</li>
<li>Each pregnancy gets easier.  Even though everything hurts more you are expecting it, and can better deal with it.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Life is hardest after the first one.  It is hard to go from “without kids” to “with kids”.  But once you are “with kids” two kids is not that much harder than one.  You have already baby proofed the house, and changed your life around.</li>
<li>Allowing comments on your baby’s birth story is stupid.  I learned that after the first one.  Therefore I have disabled them on this one.  Sorry for anyone that wants to wish us well, but one can ruin it for everyone.</li>
<li>Sleep is less of an issue with the 2nd.  To be honest we get a lot less sleep this time around.  The difference is that we know we are going to get sleep 30 minutes at a time.  And we love it when he gives us more.  With Frankie we were scared to sleep because we should only get 1 hour or so.</li>
<li>A vaginal birth is front loaded, while a C-Section is back loaded.  I am not a proponent for one vs the other, but in our case the C-Section was over and done with in a matter of minutes.  The vaginal birth took hours (31 to be exact).  In the C-Section case, all of the recovery started after the birth with 3 days in the hospital.  With the VBAC once the delivery was over we were free to go.  So with Vaginal birth (assuming there are no complications) everything happens leading up to the birth, with a C-Section everything happens after the birth.</li>
<li>Writing a birth plan, having a Doula, and using Midwifes was ideal for us.  Everyone was really supportive, and the Doula stayed with us the entire time.  The midwives and nurses reviewed the birth plan and where very engaged with us if there were reasons we had to go off plan.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Francis Alexander Kamenik]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2012/12/02/francis-alexander-kamenik/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-02T17:20:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2012/12/02/francis-alexander-kamenik</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Born November 28th, 2012 at 12:48pm.  9lbs 1oz, 21 1/4 inches.</p>

<p><img src="/images/francis/IMG_0555.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/images/francis/IMG_0556.JPG"></p>

<h2>Our Experience</h2>

<p><strong>12:30am</strong> Melanie starts labor, but can't wake me up.  It didn't even dawn on me that it could have been actual labor.  In my defense I am a heavy sleeper so it was difficult to get me up.</p>

<p><strong>2am</strong> Melanie was able to get me fully awake.  I was still unsure what was happening, so I wanted to time the contractions.  Having gone to the labor class I knew that we needed to time contractions: 511, 5 minutes apart, for a 1 minute duration, for 1 hour.  I also knew that false labor, which can sometimes be very painful, proceeds real labor but up to several weeks.</p>

<p><strong>2:20am</strong> We are DONE timing contractions!  Or rather my continuing health demands we stop timing contractions.  The contractions have Mel on the floor with back labor, and she is going to kill me.  Under explicit instructions, tears, and anger I call the on-call Doctor on Mel's behalf.</p>

<p><strong>2:40am</strong> We are at the Hospital and Mel is headed to Triage.  I get to wait in the labor waiting room until they have checked her and decide to admit her.</p>

<p><strong>3:00am</strong> We are in the labor rooms.  Very nice and roomy and private to each labor.  Big enough for a couch (where I was sleeping) several chairs, the labor bed, the baby examination table/heater, sink, bathroom, and medical supply room.  Right now it is a waiting game of doctor checks.</p>

<p><strong>5am</strong> Mel gets the epidural.  It is a sterile procedure so I had to wait in the waiting area again.  It takes just under an hour and 2 attempts to get the epidural in correctly.</p>

<p><strong>6am</strong> We start posting updates to friends and family.  We figured it was nicer to wait until at least a standard start of the day and not send the invites at 3am when we were actually admitted.  Mel's pain is much less, but so is the strength of the her contractions.  Now her progression has to be monitored more closely, and pitocin administered if needed.</p>

<p><strong>7:30am</strong> Mel has progressed to 7-8cm so we tell her parents to head down.</p>

<p><strong>8am</strong> Mel's water is broken by the doctor, but she is still progressing.  No need for pitocin, yet.</p>

<p><strong>9am</strong> Mel's parents are here.  And she is progression nicely to 9cm.</p>

<p><strong>10am</strong> Francis is still at 0 station.  He has engaged, but is not progressing.  We are on a watch because the contractions are not constant.</p>

<p><strong>10:30am</strong> Francis heart rate dropped below safe rate and immediately above safe range.  The external monitors are removed and internal monitors added in hopes that the blips were Mel's movements and not the actual measurements of the baby.</p>

<p><strong>11am</strong> The new monitors are MUCH more painful, since the vagina is not numbed by the epidural, but she endures.  Also, the progression has stopped, and Francis continues to have heart flutters.  And Mel's own blood pressure is setting off alarms right and left.  We are given the option to start pitocin, wait things out, or as the doctor recommends start talking about a C-Section.</p>

<p><strong>11:15am</strong> We had already decided that if something like this happened we were OK with the C-Section.  Mel is terrified of surgery, since she has never had surgery.  Her mother, having had 2 C-Sections, gives her the low down on what it is like.  That, knowing I will be there, knowing they will block her pain, and knowing she will be awake is enough for us to move forward.</p>

<p><strong>11:45am</strong> All the extra sensors are removed, she is in the OR, and I am sitting in the recovery room waiting to be called in.</p>

<p><strong>12pm</strong> In the OR with Mel, Doctor has made the first cut.</p>

<p><strong>12:48pm</strong> Francis is pulled out and immediately begins crying.  Normally this is great but in our case there is meconium in the amniotic fluid, so we don't want him to aspirate it.  So the peditritians take him immediately to the examanation table.  All is fine now, but we have to watch him carefully over the next few days.  It is possible for him to develop a lung infection.</p>

<p><strong>+3 days</strong> We are heading home, Francis is fine.</p>

<h2>What we have learned</h2>

<ul>
<li>Opinions due little but sully the otherwise very special moment</li>
<li>Nothing goes as planned</li>
<li>Babies have an inverted sleep schedule</li>
<li>Breastfeeding is f'n hard!</li>
<li>Breasts are purely functional</li>
<li>Nipple confusion is a much smaller concern then it seems</li>
<li>The "connection" is not instantainious for all women</li>
<li>"Baby amnesia" comes along slowly</li>
<li>You never have enough diapers</li>
</ul>


<h3>Opinions</h3>

<p>Facts are great, and even talking about experiences are nice.  But spouting opinions sucks, and we have been inundated.  Here are just a few:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Circumcision is mutilation and has a good change so killing your boy:</em> <strong>false</strong>.  Very little of this is factually actuate, but it is spouted with such fervor as to be unquestionable.  If you want your boy circumcised then do, if you don't that is fine to.  Make the choice and ignore all detractors.</li>
<li><em>Breastfeeding is </em>always<em> better then formula:</em> <strong>false</strong>.  There are benefits and drawbacks for both breastfeeding and formula.  We choose breastfeeding, but think nothing less of women that choose formula.  You have to pick what is right for you.</li>
<li><em>Never use a pacifier/bottle when breastfeeding:</em> <strong>false</strong>.  We have tried a bottle, and continue to use a pacifier and have no problem with nipple confusion.  Do what is right for your baby, your life, and you; the rest will take care of itself.</li>
<li><em>Epidural are selfish, bad, you will have problems:</em> <strong>false</strong>.  Just not true.  Mel wanted a natural birth, but when the pain of back labor was too much the epidural was needed.</li>
<li><em>Labor is a beautiful things:</em> semi-<strong>false</strong>.  I can see why it is though of as beautiful, and at the highest level it is.  But in the details of the pain, strain, lack of sleep, frustration, fear, and expectation it is more real then beautiful.  The rememberance of Labor will be beautiful - I am sure - but right now things are real.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Nothing goes as planned</h3>

<p>During our planning class the nurse suggested that we "let the baby drive".  Basically do not create a written list, because you will stress over details before labor and when things do not go as planned it will add fuel to the baby blues after labor.</p>

<p>In our case we had a general plan and almost nothing worked out as we wanted.  In the end we had a healthy baby boy and the plan of not planning worked out pretty well.</p>

<h3>Babies sleep during the day</h3>

<p>There are many guesses as to why this is, but basically once born they sleep all day and are awake at night.  Francis was born in the middle of the day, and was nearly impossible to wake up for the first 24 hours.  His bladder and bowels worked fine, so the doctors were not concerned.  In fact, almost a week later and it is still almost impossible to wake Francis after a good feeding during the day, and impossible to get him to sleep after a good feeding during the night.</p>

<p>Right now the only things we can do is keep playing with him during the day (to the point of annoyance), and ignore him at night.  By "ignore" all I mean is we can't make eye contact, talk to him, pet him, or talk to him (yes I said it twice).  We still pat him to burp him, shush, and bounce him to aid in sleeping, but nothing else.  Easier said then done, but we persist.</p>

<h3>Breastfeeding is hard</h3>

<p>One of the major opinions that is implicitly or explicitly stated is that every baby MUST be breastfed.  And as a women it should be the most natural thing in the world.  Guess what?  It's not.</p>

<p>Babies do not know how to breastfeed, and more importantly they do not want to breastfeed.  They spend 9 months being given food with no work, but now they have to work for food.  And they have to work hard!</p>

<p>Worst still a women's breast must change to make breastfeeding possible.  So even if the want is there it is very frustrating for many days/weeks.  And sometimes it will never be possible.  In our case we have to use a Nipple Shield to start the feedings because the nipples are flat and Francis doesn't know to start sucking.</p>

<h3>Breasts are purely functional</h3>

<p>When we were in the hospital there were no less then 20 people help Mel and I breastfeed Francis, and there was nothing weird about it.  We both thought of it only in terms of what gets Francis food.</p>

<p>Even now we don't bother drawing the curtains when breastfeeding.  There just isn't anything weird about having a breast hanging out in prep for breastfeeding, nor is there anything sexual about it.  They have a single purpose, which is as a food supply.</p>

<p>It is the equivalent of getting aroused by a hamburger; just not something that happens (normally).</p>

<h3>Nipple confusion</h3>

<p>I guess we made the mistake of telling the doctors that we planned on breastfeeding.  The reason that I said "mistake" is because "nipple confusion" is such a pervasive argument that they removed all formula, bottles, and pacifiers that are normally provided after labor.</p>

<p>In fact, on one night it took us and several nurses over 6 hours to get just 1/2 oz of colostrum into Francis.  And during all that time breastfeeding was the only option.  It was horrible.</p>

<p>The lactation consultant seeing the medical necessity did eventually give us a breast pump, and pacifier, but no bottle.  We had to use a syringe to provide colostrum through a tube next to a finger that simulated a nipple.</p>

<p>It took a several complete feeding failures, and finally giving Francis to the nurses so we could sleep, to just get him some formula.  In fact, we weren't allow to feed him the formula, only the nurses could and only because they could not get him satisfied otherwise.</p>

<p>It has been almost a month, we use pacifies, use bottles, and the breast and we can safely say that he has no nipple confusion.  Perhaps it is something that affects only some babies, or it is something that really hasn't been studies and is just take as fact.</p>

<h3>The "Connection"</h3>

<p>This seems to me like the female equivalent of "comparing sizes".  When asked women almost universally say "it was instantaneous", or something similar.  And I am sure 3 to 6 years after labor when first asked it seems instantaneous, but it is not for some women.</p>

<p>The "connection" is real, but it takes many days, even a week or more before it really kicks in.  And assuming that <strong>all</strong> women have an instantaneous connection really just adds fuel to the baby blues.</p>

<h3>"Baby Amnesia"</h3>

<p>It has been about a month and the baby amnesia is just now starting to kicked in.  It is definiately not as originally discribed: a clam that washes over you.  It is not instantaneous.</p>

<p>Basically what happens (at least for us) is you start forgetting the details, pain, and difficulty.  And you also start to realize exactly how much you can actually deal with.  And Francis is quite, content, and smiles and you realize how awesome it is.</p>

<h3>Diapers</h3>

<p>An infant eats every 2 hours to 3 hours during the day, and 2 to 5 hours during the night.  And they pee and poop between feedings.  You would think that 12 diapers / day is about average, but it isn't.  As adults we have learned to urinate and defecate during the same bathroom trip.  the same is not of babies.  For them they will urinate and defecate as two separate acts, and to prevent diaper rash you have to change them between each act.  That doesn't even account for the partial pee/poop, in which they start pee or poop as soon as you take the diaper off.  And in a lot of cases they will pee or poop as soon as you get the diaper back on; and in some cases do it 3 or 4 times in a single changing.</p>

<p>24 to 30 diapers / day is closer to accurate.</p>

<h2>Why leave the comment below?</h2>

<p>So a number of people have asked me why I left the comment below.  It is rude, and it is hurtful to have someone try to sully the birth of my child with "yet more opinions".</p>

<p>In fact, this type of comment is EXACTLY what I was talking about in the "What we have learned" section.  Just for fun I have turned my post and her comment into a conversation.  Hopefully it shows how ridiculous the comment is, and why I think it is important to leave up.</p>

<p><em>me:</em> Opinions suck! They lead to a lot of mis-information.</p>

<p><em>jane:</em> No <strong>your</strong> opinions suck.  Mine opinions are actually FACT!</p>

<p><em>me:</em> Turns out that Epidurals are sometimes necessary for hard deliveries.</p>

<p><em>jane:</em> No, they <strong>are</strong> selfish!  With my first child I had a beautiful natural birth.  With the second I <strong>had</strong> to have a epidural and there were nothing but problems.  As you can see clearly, it was the epidurals fault.  But I am not downing epidurals.</p>

<p><em>me:</em> Breastfeeding is hard.  Frankie wants to do it, but has such a bad overbite that he can't lock.  We have had repeated visits from the Lactation consultant and every nurse on the floor has tried to help us, but still nothing.  He is loosing weight and all we want is to get something in him.  Everyone tells us that nipple confusion can happen, but for christ sake lets get at least a little food into Frankie.</p>

<p><em>jane:</em> Babies want to breastfeed, and I also had some trouble.  I had to things like pull out my nipple before each feeding.  Clearly you guys are lazy and stupid!  You need to try harder.  Also, your are wrong nipple confusion <strong>CAN</strong> happen!</p>

<p><em>me:</em> I didn't say nipple confusion doesn't happen.  What I was saying was that we were told that nipple confusion was instantaneous.  Put your baby on the bottle once and that is all-she-wrote.  That is not the case with Frankie, but never mind you aren't listening anyway.</p>

<p><em>jane:</em> Also, circumcised boys <strong>don't</strong> breastfeed so you are double stupid!</p>

<p><em>me:</em> Wait, what?  I never said one or the other that I circumcised Frankie.</p>

<p><em>jane:</em> Well it doesn't matter.  From the way you talk it is clear that you did.  I read part of your above story, judged your entire life, and walked through all the bad choices you made (entirely within my mind).  I started writing this comment to educate you, so that your child won't be a serial killer.  Because "scientific evidence" shows that <strong>ALL</strong> serial killers were bottle fed!</p>

<p><em>me:</em> (eyes glazed over)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
