<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: fatherhood | Random Software Inklings]]></title>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/categories/fatherhood/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-22T17:30:13-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John T. Kamenik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Francis Alexander Kamenik]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2012/12/02/francis-alexander-kamenik/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-02T17:20:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2012/12/02/francis-alexander-kamenik</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Born November 28th, 2012 at 12:48pm.  9lbs 1oz, 21 1/4 inches.</p>

<p><img src="/images/francis/IMG_0555.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/images/francis/IMG_0556.jpg"></p>

<h2>Our Experience</h2>

<p><strong>1am</strong> Melanie starts labor, but can't wake me up.  It didn't even dawn on me that labor could have been actual labor.  In my defense I am a heavy sleeper so it was difficult to get me up.</p>

<p><strong>2am</strong> Melanie was able to get me fully awake.  I was still unsure what was happening, so I want to time the contractions.  Having gone to the labor class I knew that we needed to time contractions: 511, 5 minutes apart, for a 1 minute duration, for 1 hour.  I also knew that false labor, which can sometimes be very painful, proceeds real labor but up to several weeks.</p>

<p><strong>2:20am</strong> We are DONE timing contractions!  Or rather my continuing health demands we stop timing contractions.  The contractions have Mel on the floor with back labor, and she is going to kill me.  Under explicit instructions, tears, and anger I call the on-call Doctor on Mel's behave.</p>

<p><strong>2:40am</strong> We are at the Hospital and Mel is headed to Triage.  I get to wait in the labor waiting until they have tested her and decide to admit her.</p>

<p><strong>3:00am</strong> We are in the labor rooms.  Very nice and roomy and private to each labor.  Big enough for a couch (where I was sleeping) several chairs, the labor bed, the baby examination table/heater, sink, bathroom, and medical supply room.  Right now it is a waiting game of doctor checks.</p>

<p><strong>5am</strong> Mel gets the epidural.  It is a sterile operation so I had to wait in the waiting area again.  It takes just under an hour and 2 attempts to get the epidural in correctly.</p>

<p><strong>6am</strong> We start posting updates to friends and family.  We figured it was nicer to wait until at least a standard start of the day and not send the invites at 3am when we were actually admitted.  Mel's pain is much less, but so is the strength of the her contractions.  Now her progression has to be monitored more closely, and pitocin administered if needed.</p>

<p><strong>7:30am</strong> Mel has progressed to 6cm so we tell her parents to head down.</p>

<p><strong>8am</strong> Mel's water is broken by the doctor, but she is still progressing.  No need for pitocin, yet.</p>

<p><strong>9am</strong> Mel's parents are here.  And she is progression nicely to 9cm.</p>

<p><strong>10am</strong> Francis is still at 0 station.  He has engaged, but is not progression.  We are on a watch because the contractions are not constant.</p>

<p><strong>10:30am</strong> Francis heart rate dropped below safe rate and immediately above safe range.  The external monitors are removed and internal monitors added in hopes that the blips were Mel's movements and not the actual measurements of the baby.</p>

<p><strong>11am</strong> The new monitors are MUCH more painful, since the vagina is not numbed by the epidural, but she endures.  Also, the progression has stopped, and Francis continues to have heart flutters.  And Mel's own heart beat is setting off alarms right and left.  We are given the option to start pitocin, wait things out, or as the doctor recommends start talking about a C-Section.</p>

<p><strong>11:15am</strong> We had already decided that if something like this happened we were OK with the C-Section.  Mel is terrified of surgery, since she has never had surgery.  Her mother, having had 2 C-Sections, gives her the low down on what it is like.  That, knowing I will be there, knowing they will block her pain, and knowing she will be awake is enough for us to move forward.</p>

<p><strong>11:45am</strong> All the extra sensors are removed, she is in the OR, and I am sitting in the recovery room waiting to be called in.</p>

<p><strong>12pm</strong> In the OR with Mel, Doctor has made the first cut.</p>

<p><strong>12:48pm</strong> Francis is pulled out and immediately begins crying.  Normally this is great but in our case there is meconium in the amniotic fluid, so we don't want him to aspirate it.  So the peditritians take him immediately to the examanation table.  All is fine now, but we have to watch him carefully over the next few days.  It is possible for him to develop a lung infection.</p>

<p><strong>+3 days</strong> We are heading home, Francis is fine.</p>

<h2>What we have learned</h2>

<ul>
<li>Opinions due little but sully the otherwise very special moment</li>
<li>Nothing goes as planned</li>
<li>Babies have an inverted sleep schedule</li>
<li>Breastfeeding is f'n hard!</li>
<li>Breasts are purely functional</li>
<li>Nipple confusion is a much smaller concern then it seems</li>
<li>The "connection" is not instantainious</li>
<li>"Baby amnesia" comes along slowly</li>
<li>You never have enough diapers</li>
</ul>


<h3>Opinions</h3>

<p>Facts are great, and even talking about experiences are nice.  But spouting opinions sucks, and we have been inundated.  Here are just a few:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Circumcision is mutilation and has a good change so killing your boy:</em> <strong>false</strong>.  Very little of this is factually actuate, but it is spouted with such fervor as to be unquestionable.  If you want your boy circumcised then do, if you don't that is fine to.  Make the choice and ignore all detractors.</li>
<li><em>Breastfeeding is </em>always<em> better then formula:</em> <strong>false</strong>.  There are benefits and drawbacks for both breastfeeding and formula.  We choose breastfeeding, but think nothing less of women that choose formula.  You have to pick what is right for you.</li>
<li><em>Never use a pacifier/bottle when breastfeeding:</em> <strong>false</strong>.  We have tried a bottle, and continue to use a pacifier and have no problem with nipple confusion.  Do what is right for your baby, your life, and you; the rest will take care of itself.</li>
<li><em>Epidural are selfish, bad, you will have problems:</em> <strong>false</strong>.  Just not true.  Mel wanted a natural birth, but when the pain of back labor was too much the epidural was needed.</li>
<li><em>Labor is a beautiful things:</em> semi-<strong>false</strong>.  I can see why it is though of as beautiful, and at the highest level it is.  But in the details of the pain, strain, lack of sleep, frustration, fear, and expectation it is more real then beautiful.  The rememberance of Labor will be beautiful - I am sure - but right now things are real.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Nothing goes as planned</h3>

<p>During our planning class the nurse suggested that we "let the baby drive".  Basically do not create a written list, because you will stress over details before labor and when things do not go as planned it will add fuel to the baby blues after labor.</p>

<p>In our case we had a general plan and almost nothing worked out as we wanted.  In the end we had a healthy baby boy and the plan of not planning worked out pretty well.</p>

<h3>Babies sleep during the day</h3>

<p>There are many guesses as to why this is, but basically once born they sleep all day and are awake at night.  Francis was born in the middle of the day, and was nearly impossible to wake up for the first 24 hours.  His bladder and bowels worked fine, so the doctors were not concerned.  In fact, almost a week later and it is still almost impossible to wake Francis after a good feeding during the day, and impossible to get him to sleep after a good feeding during the night.</p>

<p>Right now the only things we can do is keep playing with him during the day (to the point of annoyance), and ignore him at night.  By "ignore" all I mean is we can't make eye contact, talk to him, pet him, or talk to him.  We still pat him to burp him, shush, and bouce him to aid in sleeping, but nothing else.  Easier said then done, but we persist.</p>

<h3>Breastfeeding is hard</h3>

<p>One of the major opinions that is implicitly or explicitly stated is that every baby MUST be breastfed.  And as a women it should be the most natural thing in the world.  Guess what?  It's not.</p>

<p>Babies do not know how to breastfeed, and more importantly they do not want to breastfeed.  They spend 9 months being given food with no work, but now they have to work for food.  And they have to work hard!</p>

<p>Worst still a women's breast must change to make breastfeeding possible.  So even if the want is there it is very frustrating for many days/weeks.  And sometimes it will never be possible.  In our case we have to use a Nipple Shield to start the feedings because the nipples are flat and Francis doesn't know to start sucking.</p>

<h3>Breasts are purely functional</h3>

<p>When we were in the hospital there were no less then 20 people help Mel and I breastfeed Francis, and there was nothing weird about it.  We both thought of it only in terms of what gets Francis food.</p>

<p>Even now we don't bother drawing the curtains when breastfeeding.  There just isn't anything weird about having a breast hanging out in prep for breastfeeding, nor is there anything sexual about it.  They have a single purpose, which is as a food supply.</p>

<p>It is the equivalent of getting aroused by a hamburger; just not something that happens (normally).</p>

<h3>Nipple confusion</h3>

<p>I guess we made the mistake of telling the doctors that we planned on breastfeeding.  The reason that I said "mistake" is because "nipple confusion" is such a pervasive argument that they removed all formula, bottles, and pacifiers that are normally provided after labor.</p>

<p>In fact, on one night it took us and several nurses over 6 hours to get just 1/2 oz of colostrum into Francis.  And during all that time breastfeeding was the only option.  It was horrible.</p>

<p>The lactation consultant seeing the medical necessity did eventually give us a breast pump, and pacifier, but no bottle.  We had to use a syringe to provide colostrum through a tube next to a finger that simulated a nipple.</p>

<p>It took a several complete failures, and finally giving Francis to the nurses so we could sleep, to just get him some formula.  In fact, we weren't allow to feed him the formula, only the nurses could and only because they could not get him satisfied otherwise.</p>

<p>It has been over a week, we use pacifies, and have used bottles in the hospital and we can safely say that he has no nipple confusion.  Perhaps it is something that affects only some babies, or it is something that really hasn't been studies and is just take as fact.</p>

<h3>The "Connection"</h3>

<p>This seems to me like the female equivalent of "comparing sizes".  When asked women almost universally say "it was instantaneous", or something similar.  And I am sure 3 to 6 years after labor when first asked it seems instantaneous, but it is not.</p>

<p>The "connection" is real, but it takes many days, even a week or more before it really kicks in.  And assuming that <strong>all</strong> women have an instantaneous connection really just adds fuel to the baby blues.</p>

<h3>"Baby Amnesia"</h3>

<p>It has been a week and the baby amnesia has not kicked in yet, and we are not sure it will.  At least not in the way it is described.  It is very much not instantaneous.  Sure the pain and the bad experiences smooth over time, but it is going to take time to smooth.</p>

<h3>Diapers</h3>

<p>An infant eats every 2 hours to 3 hours during the day, and 2 to 5 hours during the night.  And they pee and poop between feedings.  You would think that 12 diapers / day is about average, but it isn't.  As adults we have learned to urinate and defecate during the same bathroom trip.  the same is not of babies.  For them they will urinate and defecate as two separate acts, and to prevent diaper rash you have to change them between each act.</p>

<p>24 diapers / day is closer to accurate.  However, it is still missing the errors, the pee throughs, and the dual poops (a poop right after re-diapering).  So it turns out that 30 per day is pretty average.</p>

<p>30 diapers, 3 to 6 onesies, 1 or 2 changing pads</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
