<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: deployment | Random Software Inklings]]></title>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/categories/deployment/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-21T12:33:45-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John T. Kamenik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The 3N Rule for deployment]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2011/08/16/3n-rule-for-deployment/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2011/08/16/3n-rule-for-deployment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a programmer I am lazy, but in a productive way.  It is not that I don't do anything.  It is that I only do things a set number of times.  I have a simple rule, which I call the "3N rule", which states "I will doing something once, script it the second time, and use the script from then on".  Therefore, if I have 3 to N devices to manage then I have a script that takes minimal input and replicates the change on all devices.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I also have a 3N rule for programming, but that is a matter for another time.</p>

<p>By using a script I eliminate a lot of the human error and also increase my productivity because computers are, now days, faster at responding to stimuli then I am.  But computers are "swift idiots" so for this to work the environment has got to be controlled.  I recommend doing the following:</p>

<ol>
<li>Use VMs</li>
<li>Run headless, enable SSH</li>
<li>Use <a href="http://sourceforge.net/apps/mediawiki/clusterssh/index.php?title=Main_Page">ClusterSSH</a> or <a href="http://code.google.com/p/csshx/">csshX</a> for learning what to script</li>
<li>Use <a href="https://github.com/capistrano/capistrano/wiki">Capistrano</a> or <a href="http://docs.fabfile.org/en/1.2.0/index.html">Fabric</a> for automating change</li>
</ol>


<p>By using a VM and running headless you remove the temptation to sit at a physical terminal. It also eliminates the fear associated with screwing something up as it is trivial to snapshot a machine and restore its state.</p>

<p>By using SSH and ClusterSSH you enable yourself to start thinking about the cluster as a whole, and more importantly start acting on the cluster as a whole. If some of the servers get out of sync then it makes management more difficult, so by using ClusterSSH you eliminate that problem.</p>

<p>By using Capistrano, or its like, then you eliminate the human error entirely. This is just good policy. Also, a benefit of a deployment script is that it is self documenting (assuming you know how to read).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
