<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: concurrency | Random Software Inklings]]></title>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/categories/concurrency/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-17T20:58:46-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John T. Kamenik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Go Concurrency Patterns]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/10/17/go-concurrency-patterns/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-17T20:57:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/10/17/go-concurrency-patterns</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of Golangs strengths is its composibility.  This strength is only useful if you know how to make those composable parts.  That is where patterns are useful.</p>

<p>Golang is concurrent, which is not necessarily parallel.  However, to make things concurrent you have to break thing into automatic steps.  If you are careful in how two step share information then you can easily turn concurrent design into parallel design.  Go channels make this communication stupid simple.</p>

<p>In this post I am going to share what I think are the basis of most other concurrency patterns: The Generator, The Worker, and The Consumer.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Generator</h2>

<p>A generator simply does work and places that work on a channel.  What that means is really up to what is needed but the pattern is:</p>

<ol>
<li>Create a channel</li>
<li>Create closure which does work</li>
<li>Execute the closure as a goroutine</li>
<li>Return the channel</li>
</ol>


<p>```go
func generateInt() chan int32 {
  // 1. Create a channel
  out := make(chan int32)</p>

<p>  // 3. Spawn a closure
  go func(){</p>

<pre><code>defer close(out)

// 2. Do work
for i := int32(0); i &lt; 100; i++ {
  out &lt;- i
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }()</p>

<p>  // 4. Return the channel
  return out
}
```</p>

<h2>The Worker</h2>

<p>A worker takes stuff off an input channel, works on it, and places the result on an output channel.</p>

<p>```go
func enlargeInt(in chan int32) chan int32 {
  out := make(chan int32)</p>

<p>  go func() {</p>

<pre><code>defer close(out)

for x := range(in) {
  out &lt;- x*2
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }()</p>

<p>  return out
}
```</p>

<h2>The Consumer</h2>

<p>A consumer takes stuff off an input channel and consumes it.  There are two primary way to do this: Blocker and Signaller.</p>

<h3>Blocker</h3>

<p>The blocker form simply run the code.  This version is useful if there is a main loop which shouldn't exit until all work is complete.</p>

<p>```go
func printInt(in chan int32) {
  for x := range(in) {</p>

<pre><code>fmt.Println(x)
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p><a href="http://play.golang.org/p/7Iz7kV7soo">Here is a full working version.</a></p>

<h3>Signaller</h3>

<p>A signaller is actually a varient of the Worker pattern, where the output channel is used to signal the completion of work.</p>

<p>```go
func printInt(in chan int32) chan bool {
  out := make(chan bool)</p>

<p>  go func() {</p>

<pre><code>defer close(out)

// Work until the channel is closed
for x := range(in) {
  fmt.Println(x)
}

// Single that I am done
out &lt;- true
</code></pre>

<p>  }()</p>

<p>  return out
}
```</p>

<p><a href="http://play.golang.org/p/1LIgv1ULDy">Here is a full working version.</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Golang Steam File]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/09/29/golang-steam-file/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-29T15:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/09/29/golang-steam-file</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Go (golang) is a highly concurrent language.  But more then that it is a simple language built using modular components and string them together in useful ways.  This modularity has lead me to play around a bit and one of things that I found was a easy way to stream a file.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>At first I was very unhappy that Go did not support the default compression provided by the <code>xz</code> tool.  At work, we use <code>xz</code> to stream compress very large amounts of data.  But since go had no native support I thought that it would be a lost cause.</p>

<p>Turns out there is no native support because there doesn't have to be.  Below is the basic code.</p>

<p>```go
func xzReader(r io.Reader) io.ReadCloser {</p>

<pre><code>rpipe, wpipe := io.Pipe()

cmd := exec.Command("xz", "--decompress", "--stdout")
cmd.Stdin = r
cmd.Stdout = wpipe

go func() {
        err := cmd.Run()
        wpipe.CloseWithError(err)
}()

return rpipe
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<ol>
<li>Declare the function to take an <code>io.Reader</code> as STDIN and return <code>io.ReadCloser</code> as STDOUT</li>
<li>Create a pipe so I that can capture the program's STDOUT and broadcast it as a readable stream</li>
<li>Register <code>xz</code> as the command to execute</li>
<li>Set the command's STDIN</li>
<li>Capture the command's STDOUT</li>
<li>Run a command in the background

<ol>
<li>Run the command until there is an error</li>
<li>Close the pipe when the command exists</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Return the read end of the command's STDOUT</li>
</ol>


<p>At this point you have a <code>io.ReaderCloser</code> (which is an <code>io.Reader</code>).  You can use it anywhere you would use an <code>io.Reader</code>.  For example lets say you have a compressed CSV file.  The following code would open the file, decompress it, parse it as CSV, and print that to the screen:</p>

<p>```go
func main() {
  fp, err := os.Open(os.Args[1])
  if err != nil {</p>

<pre><code>log.Fatal(err)
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  defer fp.Close()</p>

<p>  xz  := xzReader(fp)
  defer xz.Close()</p>

<p>  csv := csv.NewReader(xz)</p>

<p>  for {</p>

<pre><code>line, err := csv.Read()

if len(line) &gt; 0 {
  println(line)
}

if err != nil {
  break
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<ol>
<li>Define the main function</li>
<li>Open a file</li>
<li>Test for errors and bail if there are any</li>
<li>Close the file pointer after the program exits</li>
<li>Pass the file as the stdin to the xz command and capture its output</li>
<li>Close the command's STDOUT after the program exits</li>
<li>Pass the decompressed file to the CSV parser and get back a <code>csv.Reader</code></li>
<li>Loop until the stream is closed

<ol>
<li>Read a line</li>
<li>Print the line if it exists

<ol>
<li>Note: in Go, it is perfectly reasonable for a command to work and fail in the same call.  If I check for an error before printing the line then I may miss the last line of the file.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Check for a stream error and break the loop</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>


<p>It is a very common paradigm in Go to take an <code>io.Reader</code> and pass it to a function just to get back a new <code>io.Reader</code>, and take that and pass it around and get back what you want (like a string or CSV row).  Once you get your head around the fact that Go's power is that everything is a small well defined lego block, and that they all fit together, then it stops being strange that you would take one kind of interface and exchange it for exactly the same kind of interface.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
