<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cat1 | Random Software Inklings]]></title>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/categories/cat1/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-21T12:22:33-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John T. Kamenik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inbox Zero / Cultivating Spam]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/01/21/inbox-zero-draft/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-21T08:40:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2014/01/21/inbox-zero-draft</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This comes from the world of GTD (I think) and is a good stragety for anyone that "lives" out of email.  I try to live out of email as little as possible, but part of my job requires it.  So I have modified a system that works well with <a href="http://gmail.com">Gmail</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Gmail has a whole app store, and I have tried a great many apps that help reduce the inbox.  Ultimately <a href="https://mailstrom.co/">Mailstrom</a> was one of the best.  I don't use it partly because my wife and came to an agreement that we would not take on any subscriptions until we have paid off our dept, and party because I am so anal about cultivating email anyway that there was very little left for it to actually move.</p>

<h1>Step 0: Getting over the fear of missing out</h1>

<p>Facebook, Newsletter writers, and almost every company prays on your innate fear of "missing out".  This fear (or any fear) causes you remain "hands-on" when things should be automated.  It drives your to "want" to read emails, read or watch news stories, or "play" on facebook even though none of those things can improve your life.</p>

<p>Before getting started automating your email you have to mentally get over the fact that you <strong>will</strong> miss out on somethings.  The fact is that you are already missing out of a lot of things.</p>

<p>Here are common fears and how to over come them:</p>

<ol>
<li>What if I miss an email about X event (where is X is a wedding, family reunion, etc...)!

<ol>
<li>Fear not, by filtering your emails you are <strong>more</strong> likely to see these message, not less likely!</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>What if my child is in trouble!

<ol>
<li>There will <strong>never</strong> be a case where a person in trouble pulls out their phone and crafts a heartfelt email.  It just doesn't happen.  If it is an email, then it is <strong>not</strong> an emergency.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>What if my boss asigns me work that needs to be done immediately, and I get fired!

<ol>
<li>If you are a personal assistant then you "live" in email and pre-processing the email will make it more likely that you find these requrests quickly.</li>
<li>If you are not a personal assisitant then there is no reasonable expectation for you to live in email.  A pre-filter that emails your boss back saying "I check email at 8am, if this is something that needs to be done before mid day tomorrow please contact me directly" is enough.

<ol>
<li>As a good employee your job is to remove ambigouity to ensure a respectful and transparent work enviornment.  And no boss is going to mandate "email" if there is clear communication.</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>


<h1>Step 1: Create some folders</h1>

<p>Nothing should ever be done from your inbox, unless the total time to read, process and act on the email is &lt; 2minutes.  If it is more then then 2 minutes then you need to place it in a folder (Gmail calls them labels) and move on.  Once the inbox is reduced to 0 messages then you can get started on the folders.</p>

<p>I recomend the following labels:</p>

<ol>
<li>"1 Today"</li>
<li>"1 Tomorrow"</li>
<li>"1 Next week"</li>
<li>"Keep / Amazon" / Any other store you want to automatically filter into</li>
<li>"Newsletters"</li>
</ol>


<h1>Step 2: Pre-filtering emails</h1>

<p>Maintaining a good set of pre-filters is essential.</p>

<h1>Step 3: Process your inbox</h1>

<h2>Marking Spam</h2>

<p>Most email is spam.  In fact, most of what people consider "real" email is actually spam.  Here are my rules for determining spam, and isolating.</p>

<p>Automatic spam is an email that matches any of these:</p>

<ol>
<li>Asks for something: money, information, etc...</li>
<li>Is a known scam: Nigerian prince with money, Court Summins, FBI...</li>
</ol>


<p>Normal spam is an any email that violates these filters:</p>

<ol>
<li>Is from a company not a person</li>
<li>Is not in response to a request made by you</li>
<li>Is not pre-filtered</li>
</ol>


<h1>Step 4: Cultivate Spam</h1>

<p>With the libral use the "junk" button comes the probability that some "good" email will be marked spam.  This is not something to be scared of.  This is something to enjoy.</p>

<p>The same way that farmers setup fields to make things like weeding easier the same is true of email.  If you didn't follow the above steps then you will find that Gmail cannot help you, just a farm that does not plant rows finds that they cannot use</p>

<p>To isolate spam:</p>

<ol>
<li>Use the "junk" mail filter very librally

<ol>
<li>When in doubt, it is junk</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Review the spam folder once a week

<ol>
<li>If you cannot determine from the "to" and "subject" if it is spam or not, then it is spam.</li>
<li>If you cannot create a filter for the email then it is spam.</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Automator - Start work - workflow]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2013/09/10/automator-workflow/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T09:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2013/09/10/automator-workflow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't like to repeat myself, and I use a Mac, so I have a great little tool called "Automator".  Every morning when I am about to start work I open Spotlight (<code>cmd + space</code> for me) and type "startwork".  The first app that shows up is my Automator workflow for opening all the programs that I need to work.</p>

<p>Here is my Automator workflow:</p>

<p><img src="/images/start-work.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The apple script (The first action)</h2>

<p>This is a template apple script that just launches all my applications.</p>

<ol>
<li>Adium - An OS X chat client that can almost all IM protocols.</li>
<li>Waterfall Campfire - My company's campfire chatroom isolated inside a Fluid app.</li>
<li>iTerm - My terminal of choice.</li>
<li>Tower - My git client of choice.</li>
<li>RubyMine - My IDE of choice.</li>
</ol>


<p><em>Note: I use "activate" with iTerm, because "launch" throws an error</em></p>

<h3>Assigning apps to desktops</h3>

<p>Automator cannot do this for you (at least not yet).  But I am very particular about where and how I like my windows setup.  Luckily the Mac remembers the last window settings on exit, so moving things around, resizing windows, and quitting does the trick.  However, it does <strong>not</strong> remember which screen an app is on.</p>

<p>To assign an app to open on a specific screen follow these steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Open the app</li>
<li>Move the app to the screen you want (using mission control)</li>
<li>Switch to that screen</li>
<li>In the dock

<ol>
<li>Right click the application icon</li>
<li>Click Options -> Assign To -> This desktop</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>


<p><em>Note: this only effects where the app opens, you can move windows to other screens anytime you want</em></p>

<h2>Opening URLs (Last 3 actions)</h2>

<p>The last three actions are the easiest way I can find to open multiple URLs in the same browser at once.  The automator task uses the system's default browser which for me is Chrome.</p>

<p><em>Note: the URLs are opened in a semi-random order.  I don't know how to fix that.</em></p>

<p>I like to open URLs as close to where I actually do my work as possible.  The trick is hacking the URLs.  These are the URLs that I use most.  Other URLs come and go - like right now where I open github.</p>

<ol>
<li>Pivotal Tracker - https://www.pivotaltracker.com/s/projects/<code>project id</code>

<ol>
<li>I tend to work on a single project for long periods of time so I just open that project every time.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Google Mail - https://mail.google.com/mail/u/<code>multi-login index</code>

<ol>
<li>The <code>/u/...</code> tells google to open a different logged in account.  I <em>always</em> log into my personal gmail account first (index 0) and my work account second.  So <code>/u/1</code> is my work email.</li>
<li>If you add <code>/u/...</code> but aren't logged into google multiple times it will ask you to login again.  This can be jarring if you are not expecting it.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Basecamp - https://basecamp.com/<code>account-id</code></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
