<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cat1 | Random Software Inklings]]></title>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/categories/cat1/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-10T10:07:28-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John T. Kamenik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Automator - Start work - workflow]]></title>
    <link href="http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2013/09/10/automator-workflow/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T09:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jkamenik.github.com/blog/2013/09/10/automator-workflow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't like to repeat myself, and I use a Mac, so I have a great little tool called "Automator".  Every morning when I am about to start work I open Spotlight (<code>cmd + space</code> for me) and type "startwork".  The first app that shows up is my Automator workflow for opening all the programs that I need to work.</p>

<p>Here is my Automator workflow:</p>

<p><img src="/images/start-work.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The apple script (The first action)</h2>

<p>This is a template apple script that just launches all my applications.</p>

<ol>
<li>Adium - An OS X chat client that can almost all IM protocols.</li>
<li>Waterfall Campfire - My company's campfire chatroom isolated inside a Fluid app.</li>
<li>iTerm - My terminal of choice.</li>
<li>Tower - My git client of choice.</li>
<li>RubyMine - My IDE of choice.</li>
</ol>


<p><em>Note: I use "activate" with iTerm, because "launch" throws an error</em></p>

<h3>Assigning apps to desktops</h3>

<p>Automator cannot do this for you (at least not yet).  But I am very particular about where and how I like my windows setup.  Luckily the Mac remembers the last window settings on exit, so moving things around, resizing windows, and quitting does the trick.  However, it does <strong>not</strong> remember which screen an app is on.</p>

<p>To assign an app to open on a specific screen follow these steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Open the app</li>
<li>Move the app to the screen you want (using mission control)</li>
<li>Switch to that screen</li>
<li>In the dock

<ol>
<li>Right click the application icon</li>
<li>Click Options -> Assign To -> This desktop</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>


<p><em>Note: this only effects where the app opens, you can move windows to other screens anytime you want</em></p>

<h2>Opening URLs (Last 3 actions)</h2>

<p>The last three actions are the easiest way I can find to open multiple URLs in the same browser at once.  The automator task uses the system's default browser which for me is Chrome.</p>

<p><em>Note: the URLs are opened in a semi-random order.  I don't know how to fix that.</em></p>

<p>I like to open URLs as close to where I actually do my work as possible.  The trick is hacking the URLs.  These are the URLs that I use most.  Other URLs come and go - like right now where I open github.</p>

<ol>
<li>Pivotal Tracker - https://www.pivotaltracker.com/s/projects/<code>project id</code>

<ol>
<li>I tend to work on a single project for long periods of time so I just open that project every time.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Google Mail - https://mail.google.com/mail/u/<code>multi-login index</code>

<ol>
<li>The <code>/u/...</code> tells google to open a different logged in account.  I <em>always</em> log into my personal gmail account first (index 0) and my work account second.  So <code>/u/1</code> is my work email.</li>
<li>If you add <code>/u/...</code> but aren't logged into google multiple times it will ask you to login again.  This can be jarring if you are not expecting it.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Basecamp - https://basecamp.com/<code>account-id</code></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
